A Guide to the Robert Adriance Collection, 1949-2002
The Edgar Cayce Foundation
The Edgar Cayce Foundation
Robert Adriance Collection, 1949-2002
The Edgar Cayce Foundation, Virginia Beach, Virginia
Coll. 33
0.8 Linear Feet 2 boxes.
Adriance, Robert
Arrangement
Collection is arranged alphabetically by material type.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Allan Adriance was born in New York City on October 22, 1917 to Thomas F. Adriance and Grace Underwood Adriance. He served as a Second Lieutenant in the United States Army during the Second World War. He married Isabel Yandalou Long on January 17, 1942 in Buena Vista, Virginia. They had three children. Adriance graduated from Georgetown University with a degree in business. He served as vice-president of the United Services Life Insurance Company and helped found the Washington Society of Stock Analysts. He cofounded the Texas franchise of Budget Rent-A-Car with friend and fellow A.R.E. member Wilfred Sechrist in 1961. Robert, Isabel and their children moved to Virginia Beach in 1956 because of Robert's interest in Edgar Cayce's work. He volunteered his business skills for the Association for Research and Enlightenment and donated the collateral to purchase the former Cayce Hospital property. Adriance helped organize the A.R.E. Press and served on the boards of the A.R.E., the Edgar Cayce Foundation, and Atlantic University (having tracked down the University's missing charter). He served as president of both the A.R.E. and the E.C.F. Adriance was a key supporter of E.C.F. research initiatives, including archaeological projects at Bimini in the Commonwealth of the Bahamas and at the Sphinx in Egypt. He died on September 12, 2002 in Virginia Beach at the age of 84.
Custodial History
Robert Adriance donated these materials to the Edgar Cayce Foundation in two installments, the first in 1985 and the second in 2000.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes Robert Adriance's professional correspondence, reports, and writings as a member and staffperson of the Association for Research and Enlightenment, Atlantic University, and the Edgar Cayce Foundation.
- Box 1
  - Comments on Work Readings, 1960-1968; Folder 1:1; Adriance, Robert
  - correspondence [A.R.E. Board of Trustees], 1949-1971; Folder 1:2
  - correspondence [A.R.E.; E.C.F.], 1969-1972; Folder 1:3
  - correspondence [Edgar Cayce Memorial Library], 1969; Folder 1:4
  - correspondence [Edgar Cayce relatives in Selma, Alabama], 1965; Folder 1:5
  - correspondence and research [health topics], 1960-1976; Folder 1:6
  - correspondence [research and spiritual foundations], 1961-1964; Folder 1:7
  - Director of Education job description, undated; Folder 1:8
  - Insight on Old Testament Passages as Edgar Cayce Saw Them, undated; Folder 1:9; Adriance, Robert
  - Israel trip materials, 1966-1967; Folder 1:10
  - minutes [A.R.E. departmental staff meetings], 1970-1971; Folder 1:11
  - outline of basic dream material, undated; Folder 1:12
  - readings extracts, 1962; Folder 1:13
  - report [Bimini research], 1957; Folder 1:14
  - reports [Field activities], 1969-1970; Folder 1:15
  - report [The Effects of Special Intervention Upon the Psychological Functioning of Children], undated; Folder 1:16; A.R.E. Clinic
  - Venture Inward Magazine, November-December 2002; Folder 1:17
- Box 2
  - Edgar Cayce Readings on A Search for God, Book I, undated; Folder 2:1
  - Edgar Cayce Readings on A Search for God, Book II, undated; Folder 2:2